Construction Manager, Office of; Collection ua332
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Office of Construction Manager Collection
1950-1980
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
New York State University Construction Fund
ua332
46.19 cubic ft.
This collection is made up of a variety of materials related to the construction of the UAlbany Uptown campus, Brubacher Hall, and the President's House.
Biographical History
The University at Albany has changed and expanded over time. Growth continued rapidly in the 1950s and 60s with the expansion of the Alumni Quad and the construction of the Uptown Campus. This huge expansion led to the institution gaining its university center status that it has maintained ever since.
The design for the Uptown Campus came on the heels of the purchase of a plot of land by the state for an expansion of the State Government as well as the construction of a University Center. The campus was designed by Edward Durell Stone, and was done in his signature modernist style. Construction began in 1962 and was completed in 1971. The vision of President Evan R. Collins to create a large University Center in Albany was realized through this work. Use of the campus by students began before construction was finished.
The SUNY Construction Fund was instrumental in the planning and funding of the Uptown Campus. Richard H. Moody acted as a liaison between the various firms working on the campus and the Construction Fund. He spent many years working for the Construction Fund, acting as the Construction Manager, overseeing various projects at other SUNY campuses.
Scope and Contents
The Campus Construction Collection is made up of various materials related to the design and construction of Brubacher Hall in Alumni Quad and the Uptown Campus. There are some basic plans of Brubacher Hall, including memos and correspondence. There are also materials related to the construction of what is now called the W. Averill Harriman State Office Building Campus.
The information related to the Uptown Campus takes up the majority of the collection. The materials encompassed within this section of the collection covers the entire range of the planning and execution of the construction. The records themselves come from the office of the architect, Edward Durell Stone, as well as the various construction firms Psaty and Fuhrman, Carter and Rapuano, Planetary Construction, and McManus, Longe, and Brockwell. All of these materials area gathered by Richard H. Moody, the Construction Manager employed by the SUNY Construction Fund which oversaw the day to day activities at the site.
Their papers contain reports on the progress in construction with individual buildings and aspects of the construction. There are also many change orders, requisitions, and punch lists from each construction firm. There are also monthly summaries from each construction firm as a report to the University. Included from all are blueprints of the land purchase and original golf course, plans for the State Office Campus and University at Albany Campus, as well as individual buildings, electrical and heating plans, and underground piping. There are also a long series of concrete test performed at the Pittsburgh Concrete Testing Facility where samples of the material were taken stress tested to make sure they were up to code.
The series are broken down by the buildings they are related to, such as Dormitory 1 (Dutch Quad), or Academic Group 1, which encompasses the northern half of the Podium on the Uptown Campus.
Arrangement of the Collection
This collection is organized into series based on the building or facet of construction they pertain too. Collections contain boxed documents as well as rolled architectural drawings. The number of rolled materials have been expanded as drawings were removed from boxes. Any drawings that did not fit in with established series were placed in series 17 and cover a variety of topics including general electrical wire planning, sewage and piping, and telecommunications plans. Some drawings are very vague with titles like “miscellaneous details.”
Items found in the archive pertaining to the construction of the campus have been integrated into the collection. Some items related to grading specifications were for a man named Michael Clapp whose relation to the project is unknown.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Campus planning; Architecture; Building materials; Blueprints; Electricians; Invoices; Materials-Compression testing; Albany, New York
- Dormitory 1, 1964-1966; 1; 10.0 cubic ft.; 209 Rolls (Roll 1, Roll 2, Roll 3, Roll 4, Roll 5, Roll 6, Roll 7, Roll 8, Roll 9, Roll 10, Roll 11, Roll 12, Roll 13, Roll 14, Roll 15, Roll 16, Roll 17, Roll 18, Roll 19, Roll 20, Roll 21, Roll 22, Roll 23, Roll 24, Roll 25, Roll 26, Roll 27, Roll 28, Roll 29, Roll 30, Roll 31, Roll 32, Roll 33, Roll 34, Roll 35, Roll 36, Roll 37, Roll 38, Roll 39, Roll 40, Roll 41, Roll 42, Roll 43, Roll 44, Roll 45, Roll 46, Roll 47, Roll 48, Roll 49, Roll 50)
  Arrangement
  Collection is arranged in their original order.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains materials related to the construction of the first Dormitory, now known as Dutch Quad, on the Uptown Campus. Materials included are change orders, punch lists, reports from the construction firm, and concrete tests results for that building.
- Dormitory 2, 1970-1971; 2; 2.0 cubic ft.; 312 Rolls
  This series contains materials related to the construction of the second Dormitory, now known as Indian Quad, on the Uptown Campus. Materials included are change orders, punch lists, reports from the construction firm, and concrete tests results for that building.
- Dormitory 3, 1966-1971; 3; 7.0 cubic ft.; 274 Rolls; 269
  This series contains materials related to the construction of the third Dormitory, now known as Colonial Quad, on the Uptown Campus. Materials included are change orders, punch lists, reports from the construction firm, and concrete tests results for that building.
- Dormitory 4, 1966-1971; 4; 6.0 cubic ft.; 422 Rolls
  This series contains materials related to the construction of the fourth Dormitory, now known as State Quad, on the Uptown Campus. Materials included are change orders, punch lists, reports from the construction firm, and concrete tests results for that building.
- Academic Group 1, 1964-1968; 5; 1.0 cubic ft.
  This series is made up of proposals, change orders, and architectural drawings related to the construction of Academic Group 1 which encompasses the northern half of the Uptown Campus.
- Academic Group 2, Undated; 6; 418 Rolls
  Series is arranged in its original order.
  Series is made up of architectural drawings and blueprints for the southern half of the Podium section of the Uptown Campus. Collection is housed on 50 separate rolls consisting of approximately 357 individual drawings.
- Infirmary, 1965-1967; 7; 2.8 cubic ft.; 67 Rolls
  This series contain materials related to the construction of the campus infirmary and includes daily rpeorts and concrete tests.
- Service Buildings, 1963-1965; 8; 6.0 cubic ft.
  This series contains materials related to the construction of the service buildings on the Uptown Campus. Materials included are change orders, punch lists, reports from the construction firm, and concrete tests results for that building.
- Health and Physical Education and Linear Accelerator Building, Undated; 9; 1.0 cubic ft.; 233 Rolls
  This series is made up of drawings for the linear accelerator and the Health and Physical Education Building.
- Library, 1963; 10; 158 Rolls
  Collection is made up of architectural drawings for the design of the Main Library, both boxed and rolled.
- Planting and Landscaping, 1963-1966; 11; 1.0 cubic ft.; 12 Rolls
  Collection is arranged in its original order.
  This series contains information related to the initial landscaping done on the Uptown Campus. Materials include daily reports on what was planted, change orders, and requisitions of new materials.
- Land Deeds and Easements, 1950-1980; 12; 4.4 cubic ft.
  This series contains the land deeds and easements for property that New York State purchased in order to build the Uptown campus as well as the Alumni Quad. This includes correspondence, legal agreeemnts, and maps of the land purchased.
- Daily Reports, 1963-1968; 13; 1.0 cubic ft.
  This series is made up of the daily reports from the construction firms on the state of the work on the Uptown Campus.
- Concrete Compression Tests, 1963-1971; 14; 0.33 cubic ft.
  Series is arranged in their original order.
  This series is made up of concrete compression tests for Dormitory 1 (Dutch Quad) as well as test for the Library and Chemistry buildings.
  - Concrete Compression Tests for Dormitory 1, Chemistry, and Library Building, 1964 (Box 1 (14-Concrete Compression Tests), Folder 1)
  - Concrete Compression Tests for Dormitory 1, 1964 (Box 1 (14-Concrete Compression Tests), Folder 2)
  - Concrete Compression Tests for Dormitory 1, 1964 (Box 1 (14-Concrete Compression Tests), Folder 3)
  - Concrete Compression Tests for Dormitory 1, 1964 (Box 1 (14-Concrete Compression Tests), Folder 4)
- Specifications, 1962-1971; 15; 3.33 cubic ft.
  This series is made up of the specification booklets related to the construction of individual building on the Uptown Campus, including the Dormitories, service buildings, and the landscaping. Each was submitted to the SUNY Construction Fund by Edward Durell Stone and Associates and cooperating construction firms.
- Shop Drawings, 1962-1968; 16; 0.33 cubic ft.
  This series is made up of transmittal sheets, shop drawings, and punch lists for the Uptown Campus.
- Blueprints and Architectural Drawings, Undated; 17; 1267 Rolls
  Collection is made up of various blueprints and architetcural drawings covering various aspects of the Uptown Campus construction.